Guide to the El Pueblo, Inc. Records, 1994-2020; 1994-ongoing RL.11105
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
El Pueblo, Inc. Records
1994-2020; 1994-ongoing
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
El Pueblo, Inc.
RL.11105
20 Linear Feet
265 Gigabytes 192.8 gigabytes transferred from El Pueblo server on a RL-owned external hard drive. Two additional external hard drives were transferred by donor. One contains 63 gigabytes of data. The other contains 9 gigabytes of data
El Pueblo Inc. is a non-profit organization based in Raleigh, NC that serves and supports the Latin American community of North Carolina through advocacy work, programs in Latino culture, health, public safety, and youth leadership. This collection contains photographs and other media documenting their events, relevant newspaper clippings collected by the organization, and administrative files related to the management and operation of the organization. Collection acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive (Duke University).
Biographical / Historical
El Pueblo Inc. was founded in 1994 in Chapel Hill, NC by Andrea Bazán-Manson (executive director 1999-2005), Florence M. Simán (health program director 2004-ongoing), and others. La Fiesta del Pueblo, their major annual cultural event was the founding event of the organization. La Fiesta del Pueblo features live music, food, arts, and community information booths. The event as well as El Pueblo Inc. itself has grown exponentially since its inception in 1994. The organization moved to Raleigh, NC in 2004. The adminstrative files available in the collection cover the executive director files of Andrea Bazán-Manson, M. Zulayka Santiago, and Tony Asion in the analog records. The electronic records include the adminstrative files of Florence M. Simán and the Board of Directors. All notes which are signed with a circled A are from Andrea Bazán-Manson during her time as executive director.
El Pueblo Inc. supports the Latino community of the Triangle area and North Carolina through a series of programs, leadership iniatives, and advocacy. El Pueblo Inc. has been involved in get out the vote and voter registration iniatives, lobbying legislative bodies on behalf of the Latino community, raising health awareness, supporting immigrants and migrant workers, promoting access to education, and public safety campaigns centered on reducing drunk driving and encouraging the proper use of child car seats. The organization also specifically focuses on youth issues and youth leadership. They have a separate Youth division tasked with running programs for Latino youth that are youth-led. Their youth leadership iniatives include the anti-tobacco program No Fumo, and Pueblo Power, a social justice and community organizing program.
Access Restrictions
Access restricted. Permission to use the collection must be granted by the collection's donor, El Pueblo, Inc. Contact Research Services Dept. to request access.
Provenance
El Pueblo Inc. Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2014.
Collection Overview
The collection consists of materials documenting the adminstration and operation of the NC based non-profit organization El Pueblo Inc. El Pueblo Inc. focuses on the Latin American community of North Carolina and Latino issues broadly. They sponsor and administer programs and events related to advocacy, community organizing, youth and adult leadership, and cultural exchange. The collection encompasses both analog and digital photographs and multimedia documenting staff, volunteers, and community members participating in events both sponsored and attended by the organization. In particular, their annual major cultural and founding event La Fiesta del Pueblo as well as the annual El Foro Latino, the Latino Issues Forum. El Pueblo Inc. gathered newpaper clippings into binders sorted by year and also a number of clippings documenting their research and interest in topics related to Latino issues in the state of North Carolina and nationally. The clippings also include promotional material for their events and other mentions of the organization in the press. The collection also contains administrative documents related to the funding, planning, management, and operation of the organization. These documents are separated into advocacy, programs, general administrative, and Youth division series.
Collection acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive (Duke University).
Conditions Governing Access
Original electronic materials and audiovisual materials are closed to use. Research Services can facilitate access to use copies in the reading room, after permission to use the collection is granted by El Pueblo, Inc.
Chapel Hill (N.C.) -- History; Civil rights -- North Carolina; Southern States -- Emigration and immigration; Education -- Study and teaching; Folk festivals -- North Carolina; Human Rights -- North Carolina; Non-governmental organizations; Political activists; Political participation -- United States; Immigrants -- North Carolina; Sex instruction for children -- United States; Wake County (N.C.) -- History; Women's health services -- North Carolina; Public health -- Education -- United States; Migrant labor; Labor laws and legislation -- United States; Voting -- North Carolina; Tobacco -- North Carolina -- History; Youth -- Political activity; Nonprofit organizations -- North Carolina; Hispanic Americans -- Social conditions; Hispanic Americans -- Politics and government; Bazán-Manson, Andrea; Simán, Florence M.; Santiago, M. Zulayka; Asion, Tony; Martínez, H. Nolo, Dr.; Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
- Photographs, 1994-2015; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The Photographs 1994-2015 series contains analog and digital photographs of events planned and attended by El Pueblo Inc. staff, volunteers, and community members. The photographs are primarily candid shots of La Fiesta del Pueblo, El Foro Latino, legislative lobbying trips, and other events. There are a number of photos of executive directors, board members, and key staff as well as NC and national political figures such as John Edwards and Ted Kennedy. The electronic records also include videos and other multimedia. Researchers would find these images useful if they are interested in visual documentation of Latino organizing, Latino culture in NC, NC State history, political engagement or election campaigns. Most images are candid shots taken by amateur photographers but there are also some higher quality images that could be used in educational or artistic exhibits, books, or promotional material related to Latino history or political organizing.
  - Día de los Niños, 1994-2006; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo, 1995-1998; 6 folders (Box 1)
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo photo album, 1998 (Box 1)
    Photographs gathered in a photo album labeled La Fiesta del Pueblo 1998
  - El Foro Latino, 2000 (Box 2)
    Includes photographs of events related to the 2000 Cenus
  - El Foro Latino, 2001-2004; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo, 1999-2000; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Staff and volunteers, circa 2002-2003 (Box 3)
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo, 2000-2002; 7 folders (Box 3)
    This portion of the series includes images of the politician John Edwards speaking at La Fiesta del Pueblo 2001.
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo and Latino Day at the NC legislature, 2003 (Box 3)
  - El Foro Latino album, 2003-2004; 2 folders (Box 4)
    Small green hand painted photo album labeled El Foro Latino 2003
  - El Foro Latino, 2003-2005; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo, 2003; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Voting drive, 2002 (Box 5)
  - National Immigration Forum, 2002 (Box 5)
    This folder contains images of Senator Ted Kennedy and other local and national politicians.
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo, 1990s, 1998, 2004-2007; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Card from John Edwards and Comunidad Sana program, Early 2000s (Box 6)
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo projector slides, undated (Box 6)
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo projector slides, 2007 Sep. (Box 6)
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo, mid 1990s-early 2000s (Box 6)
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo album, 2003; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Photographs, video, and other media electronic records, 2000-2015; 8,770 files in 311 folders; approximately 23.0 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0012)
    Pictures and videos of staff, volunteers, and participants attending events or trips sponsored and/or planned by El Pueblo Inc. Includes press materials and related media such as PSAs for programs run by the organization.
  - miscellaneous oversized photographs, 2000s (Box 22)
  - Oversized posters for La Fiesta del Pueblo and public safety campaign, 1999-2003 (Box 22)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1996-2015; 2
  The series Newspaper Clippings 1996-2015 includes newspaper clippings gathered by El Pueblo Inc. The organization sorted the clippings by year and stored them in binders. The clippings include articles on issues relevant to the organization's advocacy and events or trends impacting local and national Latino communities. Also included are advertisements and promotional materials related to events sponsored by El Pueblo Inc., especially La Fiesta del Pueblo. They also gathered clippings of any press that covered their organization. There are also instances of email and other correspondence or press releases tied to particular clippings or sets of clippings. The clippings serve as an example of the organization's research practices and institutional or community memory. The clippings also demonstrate what issues, events, or trends were viewed as relevant or important to the organization and by extension the communities they serve.
  - Binder 1, 1996, 1998-1999; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Binder 2, 1990s-2002; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Binder 3, 2000; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Binder 4, 2001 (Box 7)
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo folder, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Binder 5, 2003; 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Binder 6, 2004; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Binder 7, 2005; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Binder 8, 2006-2007; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Binder 9, 2007-2009; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Binder 10, 2008 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 2008 (Box 8)
  - Binder 11, 2010-2011; 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Binder 12, 2012 (Box 8)
  - Binder 13, 2013; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Binder 14, 2014; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Binder 15, 2015 (Box 8)
- Events, 1996-2016; 3
  The Events 1996-2016 series is divided into three subseries covering La Fiesta del Pueblo, El Foro Latino: the Latino Issues Forum, and Other Events. The series is composed of administrative files related to the funding, planning, organization, and operation of events. There are files related to sponsors, vendors, promotional material and other publicity, volunteers, and contracts.
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo, 1
    The La Fiesta del Pueblo subseries includes administrative files related to the funding, planning, and operation of El Pueblo Inc.'s principal annual cultural event. The records contain correspondence, publicity and other promotional material, planning documents related to registration and contracts, information about sponsors, vendors, volunteers, and other NGOs participating in the event.
    - Publicity, 1996-2001 (Box 9)
    - Publicity and letters, 1997 (Box 9)
    - Publicity and miscellaneous, 2000-2001 (Box 9)
    - Flyers and pamphlets, 2003-2009 (Box 9)
    - Planning and administrative, 1999 (Box 9)
    - Registration for non-profits, 2001 (Box 9)
    - Soccer related information, 2002 (Box 9)
    - Information for volunteers, 2003 (Box 9)
    - Sponsors, 2004-2005; 5 folders (Box 9)
    - NGO applications, 2006 (Box 9)
    - Magazines, 2007-2009 (Box 9)
    - Binder 1, 2006 (Box 9)
    - Binder 2, 2008 (Box 9)
      Information on event planning guidelines
    - Binder 3, 2008; 2 folders (Box 9)
      Information on vendors and other NGOs
    - Binder 4, 2008 (Box 9)
      General information and event planning guidelines
    - Binder 5, 2009 (Box 9)
      Administrative files
    - Binder 6, 2010 (Box 9)
      Documents related to sponsors
    - Binder 7, 2010 (Box 9)
    - Binder 8, 2010; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Binder 9, 2011 (Box 10)
    - Binder 10, 2011 (Box 10)
    - Binder 11, 2011 (Box 10)
      Volunteering information
    - Binder 12, 2011; 2 folders (Box 10)
      Vendors
    - Binder 13, 2012 (Box 10)
    - Binder 14, 2012; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Artist contracts, 2005; 12 folders (Box 10)
    - Mary and Parrish contractors, 2007 (Box 10)
    - Que Pasa Media, 2007 (Box 10)
    - Promotional materials, 2007-2008 (Box 10)
    - La Fiesta del Pueblo electronic records, 1997-2016; 28,500 files in 3,200 folders; approximately 31.8 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0013)
      Includes administrative, promotional, and financial records related to the planning and execution of El Pueblo Inc.'s founding event and one of its main annual cultural events, La Fiesta del Pueblo.
  - El Foro Latino, 2
    The El Foro Latino subseries contains administrative files and documentation related to the annual Latino Issues Forum sponsored by El Pueblo Inc. The records include correspondence, publicity and other promotional materials, schedules and programs of the event, and information on sponsors and other funding. Some of these files were organized into binders by El Pueblo Inc.
    - Letters, publicity, and adminstrative files, 2002 (Box 10)
      Contains a pamphlet explaing the Nuestra Seguridad program and an official letter from NC Lt. Governor Beverly E. Perdue
    - Sponsors, 2004-2005 (Box 10)
    - Event schedule programs, 2006-2007 (Box 10)
    - VIP information, 2005 (Box 10)
    - Binder 1, 2008; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Binder 2, 2009 (Box 10)
      Planning
    - Binder 3, 2009 (Box 10)
      Registration
    - Binder 4, 2009; 3 folders (Box 10)
      Budgeting, marketing, and agenda
    - El Foro Latino electronic records, 2000-2012; 8,570 files in 962 folders; approximately 11.2 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0014)
      Contains documents related to the planning, promotion, and execution of El Foro Latino, an annual Latino Issues Forum organized by El Pueblo, Inc.
  - Other Events, 3
    The Other Events subseries includes administrative files and documentation of periodic or smaller events sponsored or attended by El Pueblo Inc. including conferences and other special events.
    - Día de los Niños, 2002-2003 (Box 10)
    - Wakefield High art exhibit, 2005 (Box 10)
    - HIP Convening, 2004-2006; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - NCCADV conference, 2010 (Box 10)
    - Events electronic records, 2003-2016; 2,329 files in 243 folders; approximately 2.32 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0010)
      Documents related to special events organized by El Pueblo Inc. Includes files on Asamblea del Pueblo, El Pueblo's community forum and social movement assembly, as well as special events such as workshops, holiday celebrations, and hurricane relief.
- Advocacy, 2003-2016; 4
  The Advocacy 2003-2016 series is divided into relevant subseries such as Labor, Voting, Legislative, and General Advocacy. The advocacy series encompasses documentation related to one of the main objectives of the organization, advocating primarily for local and also at times national Latino communities. El Pueblo Inc. has advocated or lobbied for concerns as diverse as immigrant and migrant workers rights, ballot access and political engagement, state ID laws, in state tuition for undocumented students, and access to health care and education.
  Researchers interested in human rights and discriminatory laws, community organizing, immigrant and migrant rights (especially undocumented immigrants and DACA or DAPA recipients), Latino political engagement, state legislative processes (especially North Carolina), and post 9/11 immigration reform would find this series of particular interest.
  - General Advocacy, 4
    The General Adovacy sub-series includes general records related to advocacy such as health issues, religion and faith based activism, and general resource guides for community building and advocacy strategies. Includes electronic records related to advocacy, which spans all categories of advocacy work conducted by El Pueblo Inc.
    - Training on question formulation techniques, circa early 2000s (Box 11)
    - Immunization study, 2003 (Box 11)
    - Health care policy, 2004 (Box 11)
    - TPS case, 2005 (Box 11)
    - Anti-immigration emails, 2005 (Box 11)
    - White Ribbon prayer and immigration campaign, 2005 (Box 11)
    - Community resources binder, 2007; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Resource book binder, circa 2007-2008; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Advocacy electronic records, 2002-2016; 24,213 files in 3,026 folders; approximately 22.6 GB (Digital-materials RL11105-SET-0009)
      Contains extensive files related to all aspects of public advocacy organized and performed by El Pueblo Inc. Includes legislative lobbying, immigration issues, health, voting and civic engagement advocacy.
  - Labor, 5
    The Labor sub-series contains records related to the labor advocacy work of El Pueblo Inc. and any labor related work or research they conducted. It include information on labor laws, labor organizing, boycotts, and OHSA information. Researchers of labor history, NC labor issues, and Latino involvement in labor movements would find this sub-series of interest.
    - Migrant farm workers, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Nurses, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Article on OSHA, 2004 (Box 11)
    - NC OSHA, 2004-2005 (Box 11)
    - Wine boycott and construction case, 2005 (Box 11)
    - Smithfield Packing, 2005 (Box 11)
    - Migrant worker housing, 2005 (Box 11)
  - Voting, 6
    The Voting sub-series documents the voting and electoral activism of El Pueblo Inc. It includes documentation of get out the vote efforts, election information, and voting rights issues.
    - Election handbook, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Get out the vote data and materials, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Get out the vote newspaper clippings, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Get out the vote phone bank, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Get out the vote press release, 2004 (Box 11)
    - LEAP Grant, 2004 (Box 11)
    - LEAP Grant financial records, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Policy brief on voting machines, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Voter registration, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Research on voting laws, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Tides Grant for get out the vote campaign, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Volunteers, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Election protection and voters' rights, 2005 (Box 11)
    - LEAP get out the vote, 2006 (Box 11)
    - Large post-it notes for advocacy planning, 2000s (Box 22)
      Large post-it notes from planning meetings and other sessions that cover a range of advocacy issues and polling including get out the vote iniatives. Marked with relevant locations or jurisdictions in North Carolina: Morganton, Burnsville, Wilmington, Duplin County Pitt Community College, Durham, and the Charlotte Metro area. Written in English and Spanish.
  - Legislative, 7
    The Legislative sub-series documents lobbying, correspondence, and other legislative process related advocacy conducted by El Pueblo Inc. It includes lobbying efforts for both NC state and national legislative issues. The main topics covered are immigration, education, health care, and community organizing. It documents the extensive involvement of El Pueblo Inc. in efforts to gain more educational rights and access to higher education for undocumented students, especially those who arrived to the US as minors. Their efforts focused on anti-discrimination, advocating for in-state tuition for undocumented immigrants, and increased access to community colleges. Another area of interest is their involvement in immigration reform and in particular state and national ID laws.
    - In-state tuition and legal status, 2001-2003; 8 folders (Box 11)
      Contains documents related to state bills from California, Alaska, Kansas, Maryland, Oklahoma, and Washington
    - Reports, 2002-2005 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence with NC General Assembly, 2003-2005; 2 folders (Box 11)
      Includes information on the official El Pueblo license plate
    - Latino legislative agenda, 2003-2004 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence with US Congress, 2004 (Box 11)
    - ID laws and DMV, 2004 (Box 11)
    - National Advocacy Day, 2004; 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Reports, 2004 (Box 11)
    - Research on public policy, 2004 (Box 12)
    - La Ley radio DMV show, 2005 (Box 12)
    - Research on ID laws and legal status, 2004-2005 (Box 12)
    - Second Latino Day at the legistature, 2005 (Box 12)
    - Health care and legal status, 2005 (Box 12)
      Documents regarding NC Section 1011 and the MMA Act
    - ID laws and legal status, 2005; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Labor and border issues in Cornyn-Kyl Bill, 2005 (Box 12)
    - Public benefits and legal status, 2005 (Box 12)
      Related to NC House Bill 1474
    - Advocacy workshops at El Foro Latino, 2005 (Box 12)
    - National Advocacy Day, 2005; 3 folders (Box 12)
    - In state tuition and legal status, 2005; 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Community college admissions, 2005 (Box 12)
    - Mexican consulate migrant guide, 2005 (Box 12)
    - Research on SAOIA Act, 2005 (Box 12)
      The SAOIA Act was bipartisan legislation on comprehensive immigration reform proposed by Senators John McCain and Ted Kennedy
    - Undocumented students and community college admissions, 2005 (Box 12)
    - Lobbying against US HR 4437, 2005; 2 folders (Box 12)
      US HR 4437 was titled the Border Protection, Antiterrorism, and Illegal Immigration Control Act
    - Voter attitude poll, 2005 (Box 12)
    - National Advocacy Day, 2006 (Box 12)
    - Research surveys on ID laws, 2006-2008 (Box 12)
    - Legislative agenda, 2007-2008; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Legislator visit reports, 2008 (Box 12)
    - ARRA Act reports, 2010-2011 (Box 12)
- Administrative, 1992-2020; 1992-ongoing; 5
  The Administrative 1992-2020; 1992-ongoing series contains records related to the general administrative tasks and organizational concerns of El Pueblo Inc. The series includes audits, by-laws, correspondence, meeting minutes, staff data and employment files, contracts, and collaborations with other organizations. A significant portion of the series documents sponsor agreements and grant applications, organized alphabetically. The series also includes extensive administrative electronic records including the records of the Board of Directors and Florence M. Simán's administrative files, which primarily pertain to the health division and related programs.
  Researchers of non-profit organizations and their management, and institutional donors such as foundations, endownments, or government bureaus would find the records in this series useful.
  - Audits, 1995-2008 (Box 13)
  - Organizational by-laws, 1995 (Box 13)
  - La Fiesta del Pueblo site planning, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Development materials, 1996 (Box 13)
  - Meeting minutes, 1997 (Box 13)
  - Email list, circa 2000s (Box 13)
  - Staff retreat, 2005 (Box 13)
  - Art exhibit, 2005 (Box 13)
  - Apples intern, 2005 (Box 13)
  - Meeting minutes, 2006 (Box 13)
  - Newsletter, 2006 (Box 13)
  - UNC Highway Safety Research Center, 2006 (Box 13)
  - Newsletter drafts, 2006 (Box 13)
  - Collaborations with other organizations, 2006 (Box 13)
  - Consulting, 2007; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Employee evaluation, 2007 (Box 13)
  - NC Shares, 2007 (Box 13)
  - TIGRA campaign against Western Union, 2007 (Box 13)
  - Collaborations with National Council of La Raza, 2007 (Box 13)
  - Staff retreat, 2007 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous files, 2007 (Box 13)
  - Strategic planning, 2009 (Box 13)
  - Employee check-ins, 2011-2017; 6 folders (Box 13)
  - Sponsors A-Z, 1992-2008; 35 folders (Box 13)